Today, let's take a look at one thing.
今日は一つ見ていきましょう。
There's a lot of talk about rate cuts,
利下げの話は多いですが、
but why aren't home prices moving as much as people expect?
なぜ住宅価格は思ったほど動かないのでしょうか。
A lot of people still see it like this:
今でも多くの人はこう見ています。
If rates go down, home prices go up right away.
金利さえ下がれば、住宅価格はすぐ上がる。
But in today's market,
でも今の市場では、
that formula isn't really working.
その公式がうまく通用しません。
Why is that?
なぜでしょうか。
The first thing to look at
まず見るべきなのは、
isn't the interest rate itself.
金利そのものではありません。
What's more important is whether lower rates can actually drive demand.
金利が実際に**需要**を動かせるのか、
That's the key.
こちらのほうが重要です。
Even if people expect the central bank to cut rates,
政策金利の引き下げ期待があっても、
if it's still hard to borrow enough,
十分にローンを借りにくければ、
buyer demand won't gain much strength.
買い需要は強まりにくいです。
In the past, even a rate cut alone
以前は金利が下がるだけで、
could quickly loosen up money flows.
資金がすぐに市場へ流れました。
So home prices often reacted right away.
そのため住宅価格もすぐ反応することが多くありました。
But this time is different.
しかし今は違います。
Loan restrictions and tighter household debt controls
**融資規制**、**総負債管理**、
are acting as much bigger barriers.
こうした壁のほうがより大きく作用しています。
So expectations of rate cuts alone
だから利下げ期待だけでは、
aren't enough to quickly heat up the market.
市場は簡単には熱を帯びません。
And there's one more thing we need to look at.
ここでもう一つ見る必要があります。
Home prices
不動産価格は、
aren't determined by interest rates alone.
金利一つだけで決まるわけではありません。
Even if rates fall,
たとえ金利が下がっても、
people won't move easily
この先本当に住宅価格がもっと上がるのか、
if they aren't convinced prices will really keep rising.
確信が持てなければ簡単には動きません。
In the end, market sentiment has to recover too.
結局、**市場心理**も一緒に回復する必要があります。
But right now,
ところが今は、
there are concerns about an economic slowdown.
景気減速への懸念があります。
There's also pressure on household income.
所得面の負担もあります。
And people still remember
以前感じていた保有税の負担、
the burden of property holding taxes
金利負担の記憶も残っています。
and higher interest payments.
こうしたものが積み重なっていて、
All of that has built up,
買いの心理が一気に回復しにくいのです。
making it hard for buying sentiment to recover all at once.
だから今は別の重要変数があります。
So the real key variable right now is something else.
それが**取引件数**です。
It's transaction volume.
価格は反応が遅れることがあります。
Prices can react later.
ですが取引件数は先に動きます。
But transaction volume moves first.
市場が本当に持ち直す局面は、
The point where the market is truly coming back
利下げのニュースが出た瞬間ではありません。
isn't the moment rate-cut headlines appear.
買い手が再び市場に入り、
It's when buyers start coming back
取引が着実に積み上がる時点です。
and deals begin to build consistently.
こちらのほうがはるかに重要です。
That's far more important.
もし取引件数が伴っていないのに、
So what if transaction volume isn't supporting the move,
価格だけが一部上がるなら、
but only prices are rising in some areas?
どう見るべきでしょうか。
How should you read that?
それは市場全体のトレンド転換というより、
That may be less of a full market turnaround
一部エリアや特定物件を中心とした
and more of a localized rebound
局地的な反発である可能性が高いです。
centered on specific neighborhoods or individual complexes.
だから価格の数字一つだけを見てはいけません。
That's why you can't just look at one price number.
経済と不動産を一緒に見ると、
When you look at the economy and real estate together,
もっとよく見えてきます。
the picture becomes much clearer.
利下げは確かに、
A rate cut can definitely
資産市場にとって追い風のシグナルになり得ます。
be a positive signal for asset markets.
ただし、その効果がきちんと出るには、
But for that effect to really show up,
さらに条件が必要です。
more conditions have to be in place.
**流動性**が伴い、
Liquidity has to follow,
融資へのアクセスが改善し、
access to credit has to improve,
消費と雇用への安心感も必要です。
and people need to feel more secure about spending and employment.
景気の不確実性が大きいのに、
When economic uncertainty is high,
金利を少し下げただけで、
a small rate cut alone
人々の財布がすぐ開くわけではありません。
won't make people open their wallets right away.
結局、不動産は、
In the end, real estate
金融要因、心理要因、政策要因が
needs financial factors, sentiment, and policy factors
一緒にかみ合ってこそ、
to work together
本格的な上昇トレンドが生まれます。
before a real upward trend can take hold.
例えばこうです。
Let me give you an example.
ある地域では、
In some areas,
利下げ期待によって、
expectations of rate cuts
問い合わせは増えるかもしれません。
may increase buyer inquiries.
でも実際の契約は多くないかもしれません。
But that doesn't always mean more signed contracts.
一方で実需が安定していて、
On the other hand, in areas with steady end-user demand
供給負担が小さい地域では、
and limited supply pressure,
取引件数が先に回復することがあります。
transaction volume may recover first.
そしてその後に価格がついてくることがあります。
And then prices may follow after that.
だから今は、
So right now,
ニュースの見出しよりもっと重要なものがあります。
there's something more important than the headlines.
自分が見ている地域で取引件数が増えているのか、
Is transaction volume rising in the area you're watching?
ローンが実際に組めるのか、
Can buyers actually get financing?
売り手と買い手の希望価格の差が
Is the gap between sellers' and buyers' price expectations
縮まっているのか、
starting to narrow?
そこを見るべきです。
Those are the things you need to watch.
それが本当の市場シグナルにより近いです。
Those are much closer to the real market signals.
整理してみましょう。
Let's sum it up.
今の市場は、
In the current market,
利下げ期待だけで、
expectations of rate cuts alone
住宅価格がすぐ上がる構造ではありません。
aren't enough to push home prices up right away.
金利も重要です。
Rates do matter.
ただ、もっと重要なのは、
But what matters more is
**取引件数**、**融資規制**、**市場心理**です。
transaction volume, lending regulations, and market sentiment.
これから市場を見るときは、
As you watch the market going forward,
金利ニュース一つに振り回されるより、
instead of reacting to every rate headline,
取引が実際に動いているのか、
you need to see whether deals are actually happening,
資金が本当に動けるのか、
whether money can really move,
心理が回復しているのかをあわせて見る必要があります。
and whether confidence is coming back.
そうしてこそ今の市場を、
That's how you'll read this market
はるかに正確に読み取れます。
much more accurately.
皆さんの地域にはどんな影響が出ていますか。
How is your local market being affected?
コメントで教えてください。